Preliminary Inventory to the Pacific Gas and Electric Company Motion Picture Film 1960-1970
Hoover Institution Archives
Pacific Gas and Electric Company motion picture film
1960-1970
80177
Hoover Institution Archives
Sound recordings and motion picture film of a series of political education programs, featuring campaign presentations by candidates for election to major state political offices in California.
21 motion picture film reels, 3 manuscript boxes (5.4 linear feet)
Pacific Gas and Electric Company
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1980.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Historical Note
Pacific Gas and Electric Company (PG&E) sponsored this series of political forums featuring candidates for statewide office in California and discussions of leading issues in cooperation with (in 1966, and possibly other years) the Pacific Service Employees Association, International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers (Local 1245), and the Engineers and Scientists of California for the thousands of PG&E employees in northern and central California.
From a "Politics '66" brochure about this series:
"Informing P.G. and E.'s 23,000 employees who are scattered over 47 of California's 58 counties, and who are encouraged to take their individual citizenship privileges and responsibilities seriously is the broad objective of the "POLITICS '66" series. This has also been the objective of five such preceding series.
" Register, work for, contribute to and vote for the cnadidates and party of choice is the theme of the Company's bipartisan, voluntary Applied Citizenship Training program of which the Politics Series is a part. The forums provide the vehicle by which citizen employees may learn for themselves through direct and indirect exposure to candidates and spokesmen on issues, the qualifications of office seekers and the merits of propositions.
"The forums are held in the Company's General Office auditorium on the ground floor of 245 Market Street, San Francisco during lunch hours.
"Many of the noon hour programs are filmed in their entirety using a multiple camera technique known as 'Live Camera,' which is similar to television except that the finished product is on 16 mm sound film. Additional prints are processed immediately for same day delivery via the Company's internal mail 'Pony Express' to various points in the system for screening in the operating divisions the following day.
"Program Frequency: Generally a Tuesday-Thursday program schedule beginning mid-September and continuing to election day, with opposing candidates booked for appearances during the same week, is followed.
"Program Format: Following a brief introduction the candidate or candidates are allowed up to thirty minutes to make their formal presentation. However, they must submit to ten to fifteen minutes of questions from the audience. Programs are concluded by 1:00 P.M.
"Candidates or advocates of positions on propositions and their staffs may distribute campaign literature on the date of their appearance.
"Each biennial series is concluded one week after the election with a panel of distinguished political analysts, commentators, and editors who 'post mortem' the several campaigns, review the returns, and respond to questions from the audience. Like the films of candidate appearances, the press panel prints are circulated among the Company's 13 operating divisions for viewing by employees and their friends.
"Applied Citizenship Training Program: Since its inception in 1960, approximately 8,000 P.G. and E. employees have volunteered for and completed a 16 hour bi-partisan course in practical politics. Company sponsored, the ACT course has been warmly endorsed by Local 1245, International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers and the Engineers and Scientists of California.
"California Good Citizenship Committee: This year P.G. and E. is cooperating with the California Good Citizenship Committee and a large number of other California firms in providing the means by which and encouraging employees to contribute financially to the candidates and party of their individual choice."
California.; Elections--California.; Moving-pictures.; Phonotapes.; United States--Politics and government.
- Sound recordings, 1960-1970 (Box 1-3)
  - Unidentified (Tape 1-3)
  - Marching music used for programs (Tape 4)
  - William Winter (Foreign policy and foreign aid), Sept. 8, 1960 (Tape 5)
  - Philip A. Ray (Taxes, inflation, and economic growth), Sept. 14, 1960 (Tape 6)
  - Robert A. Kirkwood (Water problems), Sept. 22, 1960 (Tape 7)
  - William Becker (Civil rights), Sept. 29, 1960 (Tape 8)
  - Murray R. Benedict (Farm problems), Oct. 6, 1960 (Tape 9)
  - W. Allen Wallis (Business, labor, and government), Oct. 18, 1960 (Tape 10)
  - Frank H. Higgins (National defense), Oct. 20, 1960 (Tape 11)
  - Hugo Fisher (Proposition 15), Oct. 27, 1960 (Tape 12)
  - Ralph A. Tudor (Natural resources), Oct. 31, 1960 (Tape 13)
  - Stanley McCaffrey and Robert Crown (Presidential candidates' summary), Nov. 3, 1960 (Tape 14)
  - Seymour Martin Lipset, Sept. 13, 1962 (Tape 15)
  - John Busterud (candidate for state treasurer) and Bruce V. Reagan (candidate for state controller), Sept. 18, 1962 (Tape 16)
  - Bert Betts (candidate for state treasurer), Sept. 21, 1962 (Tape 17)
  - Sound recording of Max Rafferty (candidate for superintendent of public instruction), Sept. 26, 1962 (Tape 18)
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Use copy reference number: 80177_a_0000451
  - Melville D. Shine and Henry W. Alexander (Rapid transit), Oct. 11, 1962 (Tape 19)
  - Louis Francis and Gardiner Johnson (Proposition 24), Nov. 1, 1962 (Tape 20)
  - Joseph Eley and Guy Millard (Applied Citizenship Training Program), Feb. 1963 (Tape 21)
  - W. Byron Rumford (Proposition 14), Sept. 29, 1964 (Tape 22)
  - Robert N. Miller (Proposition 14), Oct. 1, 1964 (Tape 23)
  - Alan G. Pattee (Proposition 16), Oct. 6, 1964 (Tape 24)
  - Henry Alexander (Proposition 16), Oct. 8, 1964 (Tape 25)
  - K. E. Flake (Proposition 15), Oct. 13, 1964 (Tape 26)
  - Stephen Leonoudakis (Proposition 15), Oct. 15, 1964 (Tape 27)
  - Ivy Baker Priest (candidate for state treasurer), Sept. 20, 1966 (Tape 28)
  - Bert Betts (candidate for state treasurer), Sept. 22, 1966 (Tape 29)
  - James Flournoy (candidate for secretary of state), Sept. 10, 1970 (Tape 30)
  - Ivy Baker Priest (candidate for state treasurer) and Houston Flournoy (candidate for state controller), Sept. 15, 1970 (Tape 31)
  - Rodney Cameron, Sept. 17, 1970 (Tape 32)
  - George Milias and Homer Hyde (Propositions 20 and 1), Sept. 22, 1970 (Tape 33)
  - John Sproul (Constitutional amendments), Sept. 24, 1970 (Tape 34)
  - Senator Nejedley (Proposition 20) and Thomas J. Mellon (San Francisco Proposition A), Sept. 29, 1970 (Tape 35)
  - Sound recording of Max Rafferty (candidate for superintendent of public instruction), Oct. 1, 1970 (Tape 36)
    Use copy reference numbers: 80177_a_0000454 (side A), 80177_a_0000455 (side B)
    Scope and Contents note
    Side A - Politics '70. Side B - Politics '70 (possibly a meeting)
  - Wilson Riles (candidate for superintendent of public instruction), Oct. 6, 1970 (Tape 37)
- Motion picture films, 1962-1966
  "Politics '62" and "Politics '66" were non-partisan political education programs designed to give Pacific Gas and Electric Company employees a chance to see and hear from the candidates for statewide office in California and to understand the issues in the elections of 1962 and 1966. The 1962 series was sponsored by Pacific Gas and Electric Company and the Pacific Service Employees Association (P.S.E.A.). The 1966 series was sponsored by those organizations as well as the International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers (I.B.E.W.) - Local 1245 and the Engineers and Scientists of California (E.S.C.). All programs are black and white except for the two programs covering the 1966 gubernatorial candidates.
  - Joe Eley lecture about the history of Fabianism, circa 1962 (Reel 1)
    In part 1 of 4 of this lecture, Eley discusses what he considers the great issue of our time, man vs. the state (or individual freedom vs. society's rights). He traces the history of the Fabian Society of London, which aimed to implement socialism in England via legislation, and the Labor Party in Britain. He explains how this concept came to the United States, covering the Public Ownership League, the Intercollegiate Socialist Society, and the League for Industrial Democracy. This footage appears to represent highlights from a lecture course on politics and society that was framed around the question of the kind of society citizens want. Duration: 00:16:33.
    According to the label on the film canister, the speaker is Joe Eley. It is likely that he is Joseph J. Eley, the co-author of "You Should Be a Politician" (New York: Public Affairs Counsellors, 1959).
  - Joe Eley lecture on responsibility, circa 1962 (Reel 2)
    In part 2 of 4 of this lecture, Eley explores the alternative to the collective state, which requires examining the manifest of responsibility. If we are to be free, we must focus on the individual. According to Eley, for those unable to maintain themselves, responsibility passes to the family, and from there to the church. Next in line after the church is local government, then state government, and lastly, federal government. This footage appears to represent highlights from a lecture course on politics and society that was framed around the question of the kind of society citizens want. To view this segment, use the link at "Joe Eley lecture about the history of Fabianism." Duration: 00:05:54.
  - Joe Eley lecture on the independent voter, circa 1962 (Reel 3)
    In part 3 of 4 of this lecture by Joe Eley, he identifies the great problem of current politics, the independent voter in US politics. Eley discusses the types of independent voters, the non-voter, the casual voter, and the crossover voter. He focuses on the crossover voter as the most problematic. This footage appears to represent highlights from a lecture course on politics and society that was framed around the question of the kind of society citizens want. To view this segment, use the link at "Joe Eley lecture about the history of Fabianism." Duration: 00:07:49.
  - Joe Eley lecture on individual freedom, circa 1962 (Reel 4)
    In part 4 of 4 of this lecture, Eley addresses what is at stake in politics. He asserts that while we as individuals are working hard, politicians are making decisions about the fruits of our labor, the future of our family members, and our freedom. He highlights Benjamin Franklin's understanding of freedom, which required responsibility, along with political participation. This footage appears to represent highlights from a lecture course on politics and society that was framed around the question of the kind of society citizens want. To view this segment, use the link at "Joe Eley lecture about the history of Fabianism." Duration: 00:06:40.
  - Politics 1962: Glenn M. Anderson, Democratic candidate for lieutenant governor, California (Reel 5)
    Glenn M. Anderson, the incumbent lt. governor running for re-election, speaks to an audience of PG and E employees. Walter E. Dibiaso, president of the Pacific Service Employees Association, serves as program chairman. The program is presented by PG and E and the Pacific Service Employees Association. Duration: 00:47:28.
    Sequence: Slates begin (00:17), camera pans audience, guests enter on stage and are seated (00:54), Dibiaso begins speaking, introduces guests (01:36), Dibiaso introduces Anderson (03:18), Anderson begins speaking (06:27), first question (40:21), Dibiaso thanks Anderson and the audience, (45:14), audience applauds and begins to exit (46:08), closing credits (46:36).
  - Politics 1962: Edmund G. Brown, Democratic candidate for governor, California (Reel 6)
    Edmund G. Brown (also known as Pat Brown), the incumbent governor running for re-election to a second term, speaks to an audience of Pacific Gas and Electric employees. Robert H. Gerdes, executive vice president, Pacific Gas and Electric Company, introduces Brown. Duration: 00:53:34.
    Sequence: Slates begin (00:15), camera pans audience, guests enter on stage and are seated (00:56), Gerdes begins speaking, introduces guests (01:25), Gerdes introduces Brown (04:08), Brown begins speaking (05:41), Gerdes thanks Brown on the conclusion of his speech (34:55), first question from audience (36:26), Gerdes thanks Brown and the audience (50:15), audience exits (51:58), closing credits (52:46).
  - Politics 1962: George Christopher, Republican candidate for lieutenant governor, California (Reel 7)
    George Christopher, mayor of San Francisco, speaks to an audience of PG and E employees during his campaign for lieutenant governor. Robert R. Gros, vice president of Pacific Gas and Electric Company, serves as program chairman. Duration: 00:52:12.
    Sequence: Slates begin (00:15), camera pans audience, guests enter on stage and are seated (00:55), Gros begins speaking, introduces guests (01:40), Gros introduces Christopher (06:27), Christopher begins speaking (08:17), Gros thanks Christopher on the conclusion of his speech (33:54), Gros presents Mrs. Christopher at the back of the auditorium (34:19), first question (35:26), Gros thanks Christopher and the audience (49:59), audience applauds and begins to exit (50:44), closing credits (51:25).
  - Politics 1962: Tom Coakley, Republican candidate for attorney general, California (Reel 8)
    Judge Tom Coakley, Republican candidate for attorney general, speaks to an audience of Pacific Gas and Electric employees. Shermer L. Sibley, vice president and general manager, Pacific Gas and Electric Company, introduces Coakley. Duration: 00:45:53.
    Sequence: Slates begin (00:18), camera pans audience, guests enter on stage and are seated (00:45), Sibley begins speaking, introduces guests (01:41), Sibley introduces Coakley (04:47), Coakley begins speaking (07:07), Sibley thanks Coakley on the conclusion of his speech (31:16), first question from audience (31:51), Sibley thanks Coakley (44:34), audience exits (44:51), closing credits (45:19).
  - Politics 1962: Stanley Mosk, Democratic candidate for attorney general, California (Reel 9)
    Stanley Mosk, the Democratic incumbent running for a second term as attorney general, speaks about the attorney general's office, his work as attorney general, law enforcement, peace officer training, narcotics, the bidding process for public projects, and other subjects before answering questions from the audience. Mosk is introduced by Francis J. Carr, manager of the Tax Department, PG&E. This is a live camera recording by W. A. Palmer Films, Inc., San Francisco. In the election, Mosk defeated Judge Tom Coakley. Duration: 00:47:35.
    Sequence: Francis Carr introduces Mosk (01:25), Mosk begins speaking (04:53), question and answer session begins (25:20), Mosk thanks the audience (45:00), Carr introduces the officials on the stage (45:23), program ends, people depart, credits (47:35). Run time is 00:47:35.
  - Politics 1962: Richard Richards, Democratic candidate for US Senate, October 9, 1962 (Reel 10)
    Richard Richards, a Democrat representing Los Angeles in the California Senate, speaks to an audience of Pacific Gas and Electric employees during his campaign for the US Senate. James S. Moulton, vice president and executive engineer, Pacific Gas and Electric Company, introduces Richards. Duration: 00:48:59.
    Sequence: Slates begin (00:17), camera pans audience, guests enter on stage and are seated (00:55), Moulton begins speaking, introduces guests (01:29), Moulton introduces Richards (04:34), Richards begins speaking (07:16), Moulton thanks Richards on the conclusion of his speech (33:46), first question from audience (34:30), Moulton thanks Richards and the audience (46:16), audience exits (47:30), closing credits (48:11).
  - Politics 1964: Election Post-Mortem (Reel 11-12)
    One week after the November 1964 election in California, this panel of journalists discusses the political campaigns and election results, with a focus on California. In the election President Johnson defeated Barry Goldwater in California by more than one million votes, Senator Pierre Salinger lost to George Murphy by more than two hundred thousand votes, and in the main incumbents remained in office. The panelists are (1) Sydney Kossen, political editor, San Francisco Examiner; (2) Earl C. "Squire" Behrens, political editor, San Francisco Chronicle; (3) Jack McDowell, News Call Bulletin; and (4) Richard C. Bergholz, political writer, Los Angeles Times. The panelists are introduced by the moderator, A. Ruric Todd, executive representative, PG&E. This is the final program in the "Politics '64" series.
    Pacific Gas and Electric Company (PG&E) sponsored this nonpartisan series of political forums for the thousands of PG&E employees in northern and central California. The series featured candidates for statewide office in California and discussions of leading issues, and was produced in cooperation with the Pacific Service Employees Association, International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers (Local 1245), and the Engineers and Scientists of California.
    Sequence: Politics '64 opening sequence (00:30), scenes of audience and panelists taking their seats on stage (01:12), Todd begins speaking by introducing the program and the panelists (02:18), Todd asks first question of Berholz, about how he analyzes Johnson's sweeping victory in California, Salinger's loss, and the retention of most incumbents (09:14), the first panelist, Bergholz, speaks (09:36), first question from the audience (28:14), Todd thanks the panelists (45:33), audience applauds and begins to exit (46:09), end credits (46:27).
  - Christopher, 1966 (Reel 13)
  - Politics 1966: Houston I. Flournoy, candidate for controller, California (Reel 14)
    Houston I. Flournoy, known as Hugh Flournoy, speaks to an audience of Pacific Gas and Electric employees. Jack G. Smith, vice president, Pacific Gas and Electric Company, introduces Flournoy. Duration: 00:44:40.
    Sequence: Slates begin (00:37), camera pans audience, guests enter on stage and are seated (01:11), Smith begins speaking, introduces guests (01:55), Smith introduces Flournoy (04:06), Flournoy begins speaking (06:38), Smith thanks Flournoy on the conclusion of his speech (28:23), first question from audience (29:40), Smith thanks Flournoy and the audience (44:00), audience exits (44:33), closing credits (44:57).
  - Politics 1966: Alan Cranston, candidate for controller, California, October 4, 1966 (Reel 15)
    Alan Cranston, a Democrat, speaks to an audience of Pacific Gas and Electric employees as he seeks his third term as state controller. Fred W. Mielke, vice president, Pacific Gas and Electric Company, introduces Cranston. Duration: 00:49:11.
    Sequence: Slates begin (00:28), camera pans audience, guests enter on stage and are seated (00:57), Mielke begins speaking, introduces guests (01:35), Mielke introduces Cranston (03:23), Cranston begins speaking (07:24), Mielke thanks Cranston on the conclusion of his speech (31:47), first question from audience (32:34), Mielke thanks Cranston and the audience (47:40), audience exits (48:08), closing credits (48:27).
  - Politics 1966: Thomas C. Lynch, candidate for attorney general, California, October 6, 1966 (Reel 16)
    Thomas C. Lynch, a Democrat and the incumbent, speaks to an audience of Pacific Gas and Electric employees as he seeks another term as state attorney general. Richard H. Peterson, senior vice president, Pacific Gas and Electric Company, introduces Lynch. Duration: 00:50:20.
    Sequence: Slates begin (00:39), camera pans audience, guests enter on stage and are seated (01:11), Peterson begins speaking, introduces guests (02:11), Peterson introduces Lynch (04:20), Lynch begins speaking (11:18), Peterson thanks Lynch on the conclusion of his speech (30:55), first question from audience (31:55), Peterson thanks Lynch and the audience (48:36), audience exits (49:16), closing credits (49:38).
  - Politics 1966: Robert H. Finch, candidate for lieutenant governor, California, October 18, 1966 (Reel 17)
    Robert H. Finch, a Republican, speaks to an audience of Pacific Gas and Electric employees as he seeks his first statewide office, that of lieutenant governor. Robert H. Gros, vice president, Pacific Gas and Electric Company, introduces Finch. Duration: 00:41:08.
    Sequence: Slates begin (00:38), camera pans audience, guests enter on stage and are seated (01:08), Gros begins speaking, introduces guests (01:55), Gros introduces Finch (04:40), Finch begins speaking (09:18), Gros thanks Finch on the conclusion of his speech (29:34), first question from audience (30:57), Gros thanks Finch and the audience (39:13), audience exits (40:10), closing credits (40:31).
  - Politics 1966: Glenn M. Anderson, candidate for lieutenant governor, California, October 20, 1966 (Reel 18)
    Glenn M. Anderson, the incumbent lieutenant governor running for re-election to a third term, speaks to an audience of PG and E employees. J. D. Worthington, vice president of Pacific Gas and Electric Company, introduces Anderson. Duration: 00:56:31.
    Sequence: Slates begin (00:34), camera pans audience, guests enter on stage and are seated (01:04), Worthington begins speaking, introduces guests (01:41), Worthington introduces Anderson (05:21), Anderson begins speaking (07:35), first question (48:58), Worthington thanks Anderson and the audience, (54:43), audience exits (55:41), closing credits (55:55).
  - Politics 1966: Edmund G. Brown, candidate for governor, California, November 2, 1966 (Reel 19)
    Edmund G. Brown (also known as Pat Brown), the incumbent governor running for re-election to a third term, speaks to an audience of Pacific Gas and Electric employees on the last Wednesday before the election. Robert H. Gerdes, chairman of the board, Pacific Gas and Electric Company, introduces Brown. Duration: 00:59:43.
    Sequence: Slates begin (00:39), camera pans audience, guests enter on stage and are seated (01:06), Gerdes begins speaking, introduces guests (02:12), Gerdes introduces Brown (05:36), Brown begins speaking (08:30), Gerdes thanks Brown on the conclusion of his speech (40:50), first question from audience (42:00), Gerdes thanks Brown and the audience (57:24), audience exits (58:50), closing credits (59:04).
  - Politics 1966: Ronald Reagan, candidate for governor, California, November 3, 1966 (Reel 20)
    Ronald Reagan, the Republican candidate for governor of California, speaks to an audience of Pacific Gas and Electric employees four days before the election. Shermer L. Sibley, president, Pacific Gas and Electric Company, introduces Reagan. Actor Chuck Connors is on the stage as Reagan's guest. Duration: 01:04:00.